A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Overseas Development, International Training and Research, Administrative Files FA587
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Overseas Development, International Training and Research, Administrative Files
1951-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA587
9.55 Cubic Feet 7 record storage boxes, 1 letter document box.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Includes but not limited to: correspondence, reports, program and division memoranda, documentation of program planning, training and researh, program consultants, office procedures, and procedural manuals.
Arrangement
As received.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1951-1953; I (Box 1)
  - Area One Notebook -- Dyke Brown, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 January (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 February (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 March (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 April (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 May (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 June (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 July (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 August (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 September (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 October (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 November (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1952 December (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1953 January (Box 1)
  - Chron File, 1953 February (Box 1)
- Master Set -- Docket Items, 1954-1966; II (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal (1/2), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal (2/2), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Master Set -- International Legal Studies -- Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1966 (Box 2)
- Annual Reports -- General File re: Drafts--Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and Records Control -- Instructions, 1957-1966 (Box 3)
- Memoranda to McGeorge Bundy from John B Howard (Box 3)
- International Programs 1954 Reorganization (Box 3)
- International Programs 1957 Reorganization (Box 3)
- International Programs General File, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
- Research and Training -- China, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
- Research and Training -- Africa, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
- Exchange of Persons, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
- Training and Research Programs, 1954-1965 (Box 3)
- Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), 1952-1958 (Box 3)
- Training and Research -- Japan, 1957 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- International Legal Studies, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- USSR, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
- National Defense Education Act, 1958 (Box 3)
- Fellowship Programs, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
- Division of Overseas Activities (DOA) -- Staff Meetings, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- Staff Meetings -- Reports, 1955-1961 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- General Correspondence -- Miscellaneous, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
- Division of Overseas Activities -- Project Control -- Records, Feb 1954 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- 1960 and Prior Years, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- General, 1964-1966 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- Grant Actions, 1951-1965 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- Grant Actions, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- Administrative Reorganization -- Neremco Services, Inc., 1963 (Box 3)
- Secretary's Report on Grant Actions -- Fiscal 1957 (Box 3)
- Unpaid Grants and Unused Appropriations as of Dec 31, 1964 and May 31, 1965 -- Memoranda to and from Mr. Heald, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
- Procedures Manual (1/2), 1958-1964 (Box 3)
- Procedures Manual (2/2), 1958-1964 (Box 3)
- Program Planning, 1951-1967
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for International Training and Research (ITR), 1958 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1953 May (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1953 June (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1953 September 16 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1953 November 24 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1954 May 21-22 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1954 October 29-30 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1954 December 17-18 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1955 March 4-5 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1955 May 26-28 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1955 September 30 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1955 November 16 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1955 December 8 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1955 December 9-10 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1956 February 10 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1956 March 8-9 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1956 April 17 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1956 May 11 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1956 June 18 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1956 June 18-19 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1956 July 13 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1956 September (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1956 December 6-8 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings -- Memoranda, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1957 January 15 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, 1957 March 21-22 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1957 May 9 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, 1957 June 20-22 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, 1957 September (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1957 November 15 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1957 December 12-14 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1958 March 20-22 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1958 May 16 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1958 June 19-21 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1958 September 25-27 (Box 4)
  - Training and Research, Reports, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Report -- "Some Conclusions concerining Ford Fellowship Program", 1955 January 20 (Box 4)
  - Report -- "Recommendations on the 1955-56 Fellowship Programs", 1955 January 21 (Box 4)
  - International Training and Research -- Reports, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Training and Research -- Status Reports, 1955-1961 (Box 4)
  - International Training and Research -- Reports, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Division of Overseas Activities -- Budget Material, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Merillat -- International Training and Research (ITR) Budget, 1956-1958 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee Only, 1961 October 26 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, 1961 December 7-8 (Box 5)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings (without ITR Docket Items), 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, 1962 March 22-23 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee, 1962 May 4 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, 1962 June 21-22 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1962 September 27-28 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee (cancelled), 1962 October 26 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1962 December 13-14 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1963 February 8 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1963 March 28-29 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Attachments, 1963 March 28-29 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1963 June 20-21 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1963 September 26-27 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1963 December 12-13 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1964 February 3 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1964 April 2-3 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1964 June 18-19 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1964 September 24-25 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1964 December 10-11 (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports 1962, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budget, 1962 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budgets for Fiscal 1963-1965, 1962 July 20 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Planning Budget Request for Fiscal 1963-1965, 1962 September (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1965 March 25-26 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1965 June (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1965 September 30-October 1 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1965 December 9-10 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1966 March 14-15 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1966 June 23-24 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1966 September 28-29 (Box 6)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, 1964 December-1965 September (Box 6)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budget FY 1964-1966, 1963 April 22 (Box 6)
  - Program Planning FY 1965-1967 (Box 6)
- Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) / Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), 1952-1957 (Box 7)
  - Establishment of Board on Overseas Training and Research (BOTR), 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1952 March 18 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Minutes of Meetings and other reports, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1952 May 22 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1952 June 18 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1952 September 17 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1952 November 13 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1953 May 5 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1953 September 15 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1953 November 18 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, 1954 March 31 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR), Minutes of Meetings and Other Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, 1954 October 21 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, 1955 April 29 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, 1955 December 20 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Interim Report to Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), 1956 June (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Letter, 1956 July (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1957 (Box 7)
- Program Planning, Consultants, 1959-1967 (Box 8)
  - Secretary's Reports on Ford Foundation Grants, 1959-1964 (Box 8)
  - Grants Index, circa 1959 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Program Evaluation 1951-1961 and Statement of Current Objectives and Policies, 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Administrative Budget FY 1963-1967 (Box 8)
  - Manpower Planning and Development, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Professor Donald Adams, 1965 June 25 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultants -- General File, 1953-1963 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Robert F. Byrnes, 1958 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Neal Gross, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Melville Ruggles (Box 8)